Haipeng Yu August 2022

CONTACT Information 

# RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research interests focus on integrating high-dimensional heterogeneous data to advance genetic improvements in agriculture. Particularly, I am interested in accommodating multi-omics data into genetic evaluations of animals and plants using statistical modeling, machine learning, and computational methods. I am also interested in applying computer vision to collect real-time animal activity data and incorporating the sensor data into my research using machine learning and statistical modeling.

#### **EDUCATION**

## Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Virginia USA

Ph.D., Animal and Poultry Sciences - Quantitative Genetics, May 2020

- Dissertation: "Designing and modeling high-throughput phenotyping data in quantitative genetics" [Virginia Tech Libraries]
- Advisor: Dr. Gota Morota

## North Dakota State University, Fargo, North Dakota USA

M.S., Animal Sciences - Animal Breeding and Genetics, August 2016

- Thesis: "The exploration of a four-platform standing scale in the application of measuring temperament in beef cattle"
- Advisor: Dr. Lauren Hulsman Hanna

#### Qingdao Agricultural University, Qingdao, Shandong CHINA

B.S., Veterinary Medicine, July 2013

# Professional Positions

Department of Animal Sciences

University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida USA

Assistant Professor of Artificial Intelligence in Animal Omics Sciences 08/2022 - Present

Principal Investigator

FTE: 75% Research & 25% Teaching

Department of Animal Science

Iowa State University, Ames, Iowa USA

Post-doctoral Fellow 05/2022 - 08/2022

Advisors: Drs. Jack Dekkers and Rohan Fernando

Computational Breeding Team

Inari Agriculture, West Lafayette, Indiana USA

Computational Breeding Scientist 02/2022 - 04/2022

Department of Animal Science

## Iowa State University, Ames, Iowa USA

Post-doctoral Fellow 08/2020 - 02/2022

Advisors: Drs. Jack Dekkers and Rohan Fernando

Affiliated Positions University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida USA

• University of Florida Genetics Institute Faculty Member

08/2022 - Present

Work Experience Department of Animal and Poultry Sciences

Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Virginia USA

• Graduate Research Assistant 08/2018 - 05/2020

• Graduate Teaching Assistant

Spring 2019 and Spring 2020

Department of Animal Science

University of Nebraska-Lincoln, Lincoln, Nebraska USA

• Graduate Research Assistant 08/2016 - 08/2018

Department of Animal Sciences

North Dakota State University, Fargo, North Dakota USA

• Graduate Teaching Assistant 08/2015 - 05/2016

• Graduate Research Assistant

01/2015 - 05/2016

Professional society memberships

- American Dairy Science Association. 2021 Present
- American Society of Animal Science. 2017 Present

EDITORIAL ACTIVITIES

## Ad Hoc Reviewer

• Number of manuscripts reviewed per journal: BMC Plant Biology (1), Frontiers in Animal Science (1), Journal of Animal Science (5), Scientific Reports (1), The Plant Genome (1)

PEER REVIEWED
JOURNAL ARTICLES

6 first author and 5 co-author

2021

- 11. Clevinger EM, Biyashev R, Lerch-Olson E, <u>Yu H</u>, Quigley C, Song Q, Dorrance AE, Robertson AE, Saghai Maroof MA. Identification of Quantitative Disease Resistance Loci towards Four Pythium Species in Soybean. *Frontiers in Plant Science*. 12:644746. doi: 10.3389/fpls.2021.644746
- 10. Pegolo S, <u>Yu H</u>, Morota G, Bisutti V, Rosa GJM, Bittante G, and Cecchinato A. Structural equation modelling for unravelling the multivariate genomic architecture of milk proteins in dairy cattle. *Journal of Dairy Science*. 104:5705-5718. doi: 10.3168/jds.2020-18321

- Yu H and Morota G. GCA: An R package for genetic connectedness analysis using pedigree and genomic data. BMC Genomics. 22:119. doi: 10.1186/s12864-021-07414-7
- 8. <u>Yu H</u>, Lee K, and Morota G. Forecasting dynamic body weight of non-restrained pigs from images using an RGB-D sensor camera. *Translational Animal Science*. **5**:1-9. doi: 10.1093/tas/txab006
- 7. Momen M, Bhatta M, Hussain W, Yu H, and Morota G. Modeling multiple phenotypes in wheat using data-driven genomic exploratory factor analysis and Bayesian network learning. *Plant Direct.* **00**:e00304. doi: 10.1002/pld3.304
- Amorim ST, <u>Yu H</u>, Momen M, de Albuquerque, LG, Pereira, ASC, Baldi F, and Morota G. An assessment of genomic connectedness measures in Nellore cattle. *Journal of Animal Science*. 98:1-12. doi: 10.1093/jas/skaa289
- 5. Yu H, Morota G, Celestino EF, Dahlen CR, Wagner SA, Riley DG, and Hanna LLH. Deciphering cattle temperament measures derived from a four-platform standing scale using genetic factor analytic modeling. *Frontiers in Genetics.* 11:599. doi: 10.3389/fgene.2020.00599
- 4. Hanna LLH, Hieber JK, <u>Yu H</u>, Celestino Jr EF, Dahlen CR, Wagner SA, and Riley DG. Blood collection has negligible impact on scoring temperament in Angus-based weaned calves. *Livestock Science*. 230:103835. doi: 10.1016/j.livsci.2019.103835
- 3. <u>Yu H</u>, Campbell MT, Zhang Q, Walia H, and Morota G. Genomic Bayesian confirmatory factor analysis and Bayesian network to characterize a wide spectrum of rice phenotypes. *G3: Genes, Genomes, Genetics.* **9**:1975-1986. doi: 10.1534/g3.119.400154
- 2. <u>Yu H</u>, Spangler ML, Lewis RM, and Morota G. Do stronger measures of genomic connectedness enhance prediction accuracies across management units? *Journal of Animal Science*. **96**:4490-4500. doi: 10.1093/jas/sky316
- 1. <u>Yu H</u>, Spangler ML, Lewis RM, and Morota G. Genomic relatedness strengthens genetic connectedness across management units. *G3: Genes, Genomes, Genetics.* **10**:3543-3556. doi: 10.1534/g3.117.300151

PEER REVIEWED CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS

2022

2020

2019

2018

2017

- 3. Yu H, van Milgen J, Knol EF, Fernando RL, and Dekkers JCM. 2022. A bayesian hierarchical model to integrate a mechanistic growth model in genomic prediction. In: *Proceedings*, 12th World Congress of Genetics Applied to Livestock Production. July 3-8, Rotterdam, The Netherlands. [PDF]
- 2. Dekkers JCM, Su H, Kramer L, and Yu H. 2022. An approach for the design of breeding programs using genomics. In: *Proceedings, 12th World Congress of Genetics Applied to Livestock Production*. July 3-8, Rotterdam, The Netherlands. [PDF]
- Ni Z, Fernando RL, <u>Yu H</u>, Knol EF, Dekkers JCM. 2022. Genomic prediction of longitudinal body weights in pigs using a neural network. In: *Proceedings*, 12th World Congress of Genetics Applied to Livestock Production. July 3-8, Rotterdam, The Netherlands. [PDF]

2018

1. Yu H, Spangler ML, Lewis RM, and Morota G. 2018. Stronger measures of genomic connectedness enhance prediction accuracies across management units. In: Proceedings, 11th World Congress of Genetics Applied to Livestock Production. 11:406. February 11-16, Auckland, New Zealand. [PDF]

## BIORXIVED MANUSCRIPTS

1. Campbell M, <u>Yu H</u>, Momen M, and Morota G. Examining the relationships between phenotypic plasticity and local environments with genomic structural equation models. *bioRxiv*. doi: 10.1101/2019.12.11.873257

## Invited Presentations

2022

- 2. Integrating High-dimensional Heterogeneous Omics Data to Advance Animal Agriculture Using Artificial Intelligence. UF/IFAS Artificial Intelligence Summit. University of Florida. June 21.
- 1. Bayesian hierarchical inference to integrate a nutritional growth model into genomic evaluation of pigs. Feed Platform Meeting. Topigs Norsvin. Online. April 21.

## Contributed Presentations

2021

 A Bayesian hierarchical model to integrate growth models into genomic evaluation of pigs. ASAS-CSAS-SSASAS Annual Meeting and Trade Show. Online. July 14-23.

2020

- **6**. Development of image analysis pipeline to predict body weight in pigs. EAAP Annual Meeting 2020. Online. December 3.
- 5. Development of image analysis pipeline to predict body weight in pigs. ASAS-CSAS-WSASAS Virtual Annual Meeting and Trade Show. Online. July 19-23.

2019

4. Precision agriculture on cattle temperament: Utilizing factor analysis and multi-trait modeling to characterize a four-platform standing scale. NCERA-225 Annual Meeting. Implementation and Strategies for National Beef Cattle Genetic Evaluation. Blacksburg, VA. October 10-11.

2018

 An assessment of genomic relatedness across management units. ADSA-ASAS 2018 Midwest Meeting. Omaha, NE. March 12-14.

2017

- Stronger measures of genomic connectedness enhance prediction accuracies across management units. NCERA-225 Annual Meeting. Implementation and Strategies for National Beef Cattle Genetic Evaluation. Stanley Stout Livestock Marketing Center, Manhattan, KS. October 18-19.
- 1. Genomic relatedness strengthens genetic connectedness across management units. ASAS-CSAS Annual Meeting and Trade Show. Baltimore, MD. July 8-12.

## Intramural Seminars

2021

• Animal Breeding and Genetics seminar. Department of Animal Science, Iowa State University. September 3.

2020

- Animal Breeding and Genetics Graduate Student Organization seminar. Department of Animal Science, Iowa State University. October 2.
- Animal Breeding and Genetics seminar. Department of Animal Science, Iowa State University. September 18.
- Ph.D. Thesis Defense. Department of Animal and Poultry Sciences, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. March 18.

2019

- Ninth Annual Animal and Poultry Sciences Research Symposium. Department of Animal and Poultry Sciences, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. May 21.
- The Reproductive Biology Club. Department of Animal and Poultry Sciences, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. April 19.

2018

• Animal Breeding and Genetics seminar. Department of Animal Science, University of Nebraska-Lincoln. February 28.

2017

- Animal Breeding and Genetics seminar. Department of Animal Science, University of Nebraska-Lincoln. February 14.
- Animal Breeding and Genetics Seminars. Department of Animal Sciences, University of Nebraska-Lincoln. September 29.
- 2016
- M.S. Thesis Defense. Department of Animal Sciences, North Dakota State University. May 17.

#### Teaching

#### Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Virginia, USA

#### Guest Instructor

• GWAS Workshop [Slides]

**Summer 2019** 

#### Graduate Teaching Assistant

• APSC 5984/20816: Complex Trait Genomics [WWW]

Spring 2020

• ALS 3104: Animal Breeding and Genetics

Spring 2019

## <u>Tutorials</u>

- Factor Analytic Model [WWW]
- Gaussian Bayesian Network [WWW]
- Structural Equation Model GWAS [WWW]

## University of Nebraska-Lincoln, Lincoln, Nebraska, USA

#### Guest Instructor

• ASCI 944 / STAT 844 Quantitative Methods for Genomics of Complex Traits Spring 2018 [Slides] [WWW]

# North Dakota State University, Fargo, North Dakota USA Graduate Teaching Assistant

• ANSC 357: Animal Genetics

Spring 2016

• AGRI 189: Skills for Academic Success

Fall 2015

# SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENTS

## R package

• GCA - https://github.com/HaipengU/GCA

## PARTICIPATION IN MEETINGS, SYMPOSIUMS, AND WORKSHOPS

2021

• Poultry Breeder's Roundtable & National Swine Improvement Federation Joint Meeting. Marriott St. Louis Grand, St. Louis, MO. November 30 - December 2.

2020

- The 6th International Conference of Quantitative Genetics. Online. November 2-12.
- The Plant and Animal Genome XXVIII Conference. Town and Country Hotel, San Diego, CA. January 11-15.

2015

- NCERA-225 Annual Meeting. Implementation and Strategies for National Beef Cattle Genetic Evaluation. North Dakota State University, ND. October 22-23.
- Graduate Learning Conference for College Teaching. North Dakota State University, ND. August 17-18.
- WERA-1: Beef Cattle Breeding in the Western Region. Miles City, MT. May 19-20.
- ADSA-ASAS Midwest Meeting. Des Moines, IA. March 15-18.

## Honors/ Awards

2020

• The 6th International Conference of Quantitative Genetics US-Based Early Career Researcher Scholarship. Online. November.

2019

- 24th Summer Institute in Statistical Genetics (SISG) Scholarship, University of Washington, Seattle, WA, July.
- Ninth Annual Animal and Poultry Sciences Research Symposium Travel Award \$400, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, May.

2015

• Frank Bain Graduate Student Scholarship \$1,650, North Dakota State University, Spring.

2009-2013

• Outstanding Undergraduate Scholarship, Qingdao Agricultural University, China.

## Additional Training

2019

- Deep Learning for Computer Vision Workshop, Virginia Tech, VA, September 6.
- 24th Summer Institute in Statistical Genetics (SISG), University of Washington, Seattle, WA, July 17-24.

2018

• Programming and Computer Algorithms in Animal Breeding With Focus on Genomic Selection and Single-Step GBLUP, University of Georgia, GA, May 7-25.

2017

- Introduction to Graphical Models With Applications to Quantitative Genetics and Genomics, Iowa State University, IA, June 19-23.
- Software Carpentry Workshop. University of Nebraska-Lincoln, NE, January 5-6.